Hello, I'm Dr. Pak Jong Cheol. Today I'm going to talk about implant fixtures.
These days each of many companies sell various fixtures.
If we had the wondering of the lord of the rings, it would have been easier which product to use.
However, the reality is not that simple. Therefore, we need to choose which fixture to use.
Therefore, we need to understand the fixtures to make a good choice.
So, from today through three lectures we are going to study fixtures.
Today is the first lecture and we are going to look at why have implanted fixtures been changed and what are their merited merits.
If you look at here there are three types of fixtures.
Today, most implants are one of these three.
The very first modern implant design to be placed at the ball level is the external type. All stem cells that type under the name of US.
The implant that is placed at the gingival level is a tissue level implant or stem cells it under the name of SS.
And the internal submerged implants is placed below the bone level or stem cells it under the name of tears.
So these three implants are in the mainstream.
What type of implants do we need to use if you use them appropriately they can last for a long time external type tissue level type implant.
Internal submerged type implant.
So as you can see in the cases, whatever the design may be. If you use it appropriately they can be maintained pretty well.
Then why if we have implanted the fixtures being changed?
The first widely used implant prone external fixture.
If it was perfect, I don’t think the changes would have been necessary.
It was not perfect. So the design has been changed.
So we will look at why and how implant fixtures have been changed.
So, we'll look at how the fixtures have been changed over the three lectures. We are going to look at fixture design implant materials.
And the fixture surface treatment methods. How such changes would affect the implant treatment and then summary
First, the fixture design changes and implant material changes will be discussed.
The implants used for implant treatment are usually these three.
First, the external type implant austem has the brabd bane US for this type.
The connection between the fixture and the abutment is located outside.
This is the structure of the external implant.
The structure in the fixture is called the module.
If you look at the crystal module there is the hexagonal top on the platform. The hexagonal top will be connected to on abutment.
On top of it, the connection between the fixture and the abutment is located outside.
Such connection has some problems like this.
The connection is outside that means microleakage can occur leading to the resorption of bone like this.
Another problem is the difficulty in doing the surgery.
When the bone height is not consistent in the surgical area and the height of consecutive fixtures is not appropriate.
The height of bone will converge to the low bone height.
The marginal bone of the implant placed in the higher bone is often resolved.
When the bone height is not consistent depending on the location of the fixture and how bone graft is done.
The outcome may become fatal. Thus, the difficulty in surgery.
The biggest weakness of the external implants the marginal bond absorption is overcome.
With a tissue level implant, I don’t know if it was devised to address the problem. The cuff part of the abutment is included in the fixture body of tissue level implant.
This is the structure of the tissue level implant.
The crystal module looks different from the external type.
Then what has changed.
Broadly, four things can be discussed.
First, one piece implant.
Second, the implant is placed at the tissue level. The gingival level.
Third, the connection between the fixture and the abutment is located inside the fixture.
Fourth, the connection between the fixture and the abutment is tapered.
The structure of the fixture does have changed. I've overcome the disadvantages of the external type.
In the one piece structure the prosthesis is connected at the gingival level.
So there is no microleakage.
And the appropriate soft tissue can be secured and abutment fixture connection part is inside the fixture so it leads to less micro movement and less screw loosening.
Therefore, marginal bone stability has been achieved evidence by many papers.
Actually, very good clinical outcome has been achieved.
So the tissue level implant has very good outcome.
So, one body incorporating the abutment in the fixture emerged.
The screw connection between the fixture and the abutment has been completely eliminated.
There are advantages with that but if implant positioning is a little bit off, fabricating prosthesis is very difficult.
And when you need a bone grafting two-stage surgery is necessary but it is not possible with this implant.
Therefore, it is only used in a narrow region like a lower anterior or to fabricate a provisional tool or to maintain a denture.
So it is using a limited scope. The one body incorporating the abutment is not really used widely.
As implant transitioned from the external to tissue level implant there has been many advantages.
But, there are about three limitations. First,
The prostetic option limitation.
When the inner arch distance is short the implanted cuff is hard to adjust.
Prosthetic shape is not very good they can fall off frequently.
Two, in the aesthetic area the abutment cannot be adjusted.
Therefore, aesthetically it is challenging.
Third, when the height of bone is not consistent. If the implant is placed based on the higher bone level like medial,
Threads of the implant are exposed at the distal side.
If you place an implant based on lower bone level at the distal side, it is placed too deep at the mesial side.
So it is very challenging to determine the vertical positions of the fixture during surgery.
It feels uncomfortable to expose the threads. So mostly they are placed a  little deep like this.
If you place an implanted deep, that should not go deep like near the adjacent tooth you will not feel comfortable with it.
In actual clinical setting the acutal tissue level implant is placed very deep which results in deep bone resorption.
In another case, the tissue level implant is placed at the bone level.
Severe bone resorption occurred. So there are many advantages but surgical and prosthetic limitations exist.
For the tissue level implant. The problem of the tissue level implant. The abutment cuff which is part of the fixture removed.
And the advantage of the implant which is the internal connection is adapted in the internal submerged implant.
It brings greater surgical convenience to dentists.
It has various prosthetic options, excelletn aesthetic solution and the breakthrough design.
The platform switching design and it is most widely used currently.
When there is inconsistent bone level, unlike the conventional implants like external or tissue level implants.
Stability in the marginal bone is achieved which was hard to get before.
Internal submerged implant structure.
Internal structure and platform switching are the characteristics of the crystal module, looks like this.
Internal submerged type implant and the tissue level implant.
Fixtures have the internal connection with the abutment that is the same but,
The internal connection shape is different. The hex versus octa tissue level implant. The abutment connection.
There is a stop at the fixture but in the internal submerged implant there is no such stuff due to the difference.
The internal submerged implants have many problems.
There's a high risk of fracture due to thinner wall of the fixture.
Second, the abutment connection structure does not have a stop.
Therefore, sink down can occur.
Third, In thin biotype if the implant is placed shallow and fatal bone resorption can occur that is the disadvantage of the intra-submerged implant.
Let's look at how body types have change.
At the beginning, the body of implant mostly were straight.
When bone quality is good that's not a problem but when the bone quality is weak initial stability is low and
and creates a problem for implant healing in order to address that implant has been made a tapered.
In order to increase the initial stability and the healing.
The straight fixture as you can see here. The first thread is passing and the other threads are following the thread.
Therefore, the torque is maintained the consistent. The taper body type fixture when placing the implant high torque is achieved due to tapered shape and self-tapping capacity.
It is advantageous for early loading and immediate placement.
Taper body type fixture shows a higher contact with the bone.
Therefore, this fixture can create higher initial stability. Please keep that in mind and then you will be able to understand better the process of implanted healing in the next lecture.
Taper implant has another advantage, The implant apex passes through the entry point of the drilled hole reducing the installation time.
As you can see, the fixtures do not have interferance at the entrance.
If it is a highly tapered double threaded implant it can be placed with just a three or four rotations.
Another advantage of the taper type fixture is when bown becomes narrower.
The taper shape can prevent the damage to the roots of adjacent teeth as you can see in the picture.
Currently, there are various degree of taper but tapered body implants are mainly used.
next implant materials.
The requirement for the implant materials most important one is the biocompatibility.
Biocompatibilty means it should not cause inflamatory reaction in the body and it should not interfere with the cell growth.
No matter how good the physical property may be. It should not generate any harmful effect in the body.
Professor Purunemak got the idea of using titanium while experimenting with rabbits.
Now, a lot of titanium implants are produced.
In the past, people thought pure titanium should be used only but where high strength is required titanium alloy
Including aluminum or vanadium is used.
Recently Zirconia including alloy is being developed I cannot cover all of them. Today I'm going to focus on the titanium which is most widely used material.
Titanium is the most representative bioinert material when it goes into body there is no negative reaction to the tissue.
In the body, it forms highly stabilized oxide film and it is highly corrosion resistant.
It is classified in degrees 1 through 4 depending on the contents of oxygen and iron.
Titanium is a metal so ion can come out that can work very adversely in a living body.
But, titanium in body forms a stabilized oxide layer. It's thickness is about 200 nanometer.
The oxide layer enables the osseointegration so titanium it can be used as a safe materials for implants.
People used to think pure titanium can be used only but as a higher strength material is required for implants.
Titainum alloy with aluminum and vanadium was developed.
So grade 1 to 4 are pure titanium and grade 5 is alloy titanium.
From grade 1 to grade 5, In that direction the strength goes up but biocompatibility is decreased.
On the contrary , as you go toward the grade one strength would go down but biocompatibility will increase.
There used to be huge controversy over pure titanium vs alloy but it has subsided.
Right now, where high strength is required the small diameter implants or superstructure abutment or screws use grade 5 titanium.
And in other parts grade 4 titanium is used.
So let's summarize what we have discussed.
Fixture desing and materials.
Fixture design has external tissue level and internal submerged implants three designs.
Which one is good or bad is irrelevant. Each of them has advantages and disadvantages.
Therefore, we need to understand advantages and disadvantages properly with any implant you can get very good outcome if you use it appropriately.
Depending on the type of the fixture body. It is classified into straight and taper, personally  I don’t use straight type.
I used taper implants with good initial stability and relatively good stability with adjacent structure.
Grade 5 titanium alloy is used where high strength is required such as narrow implants, superstructure of implants.
And for other parts grade 4 is used which has with proper biocompatibility and strength.
Today, we talked about fixture and design materials this concludes the lecture.
I'll come back to the second fixture lecture.
Thank you very much for your listening.